Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Communist Party of the United States of America PE.031
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Communist Party of the United States of America
1918-2004
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
PE.031
13.5 Linear Feet in 10 record cartons, 5 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize flat box, and 3 shared boxes
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Communist Party of the United States of America (1918-2004) is an artificial collection, collected and assembled by the Tamiment Library over the course of several decades. It consists of a wide selection of printed matter produced by the CPUSA from the 1920s up through 2004. This includes fliers, brochures, open letters, constitutions, pamphlets and other publications, offering both a general introduction to the CPUSA as well as an in depth look into the types of public material produced by the organization. Also included in the collection is material from various state and local parties, with a large portion coming from New York State and New York City. There are also materials from the CPUSA's various youth affiliates, the Young Communist League and the Young Workers Liberation League as well as from CPUSA antecedants and affiliated organizations. Lastly, the collection consists of pamphlets put out by CPUSA presses, including their paper, The Daily Worker, and such publishing houses as International Publishers, New Century Publishers, and Workers Library Publishers.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Custodial History
The provenance of the materials is varied. Items were obtained through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and through ongoing collecting by Tamiment staff.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into five series. Folders are arranged alphabetically within series. The series arrangement of the records is as follows:
Series I: CPUSA General Files, 1920-2004
Series II: CPUSA State and Local Files, 1929-1987
Series III: Affiliated and Youth Organizations, 1918-1987
Series IV: Presses and Publishing Houses, 1920-1998
Series V: Oversize, 1932-1949
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Communist Party of the USA Records (TAM 132)
Communist Party of the USA Photographs (PHOTOS 223)
Scope and Content Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Communist Party of the United States of America (1918-2004) consists of constitutions, convention proceedings, reports, memoranda and press releases as well as printed ephemera such as fliers, brochures, circular letters, newspapers clippings, pamphlets and publications.
Series I: CPUSA General Files, 1920-1987, contains a wide selection of printed material put out by the CPUSA at the national level. When noted, material has been separated by committee, commission or department, with a large portion coming from the Central Committee, the National Campaign Committee, and the National Education Department, though there are also files on the National Farm, Negro, Teachers, Veterans, and Women's Commissions.
Series II: CPUSA State and Local Files, 1929-1987, contains material generated by various state and local parties. Series II is broken down into two Sub-series, Sub-series A being material from New York State, District and City, and Sub-series B being material from all other states and locals. When noted, the material in Sub-series A is divided by department or committee, with a large portion coming from the National Education Department, in the form of club discussion guides, course curricula and publications relating to National Negro Week celebrated by the CPUSA in the early 1950s. This section also contains fliers, brochures, and pamphlets from the Election Campaign Committee outlining different electoral platforms and programs supported by the New York State Communist Party. There are also a number of pamphlets published by the New York State Communist Party included in this Sub-series as well.
Series III: Affiliated And Youth Organizations, 1918-1987, contains material put out by groups affiliated with the Communist Party of the United States of America. These include predecessor, break away, affiliated and youth groups. A large portion of Series III comes from the youth wings of the CPUSA, the Young Communist League (YCL) and the Young Workers Liberation League. The Young Communist League material is separated by local, with material largely coming from various New York City colleges including Brooklyn College and City College. There is also YCL material from Massachusetts, Illinois, and the National Education Department included here.
Series IV: Presses and Publishing Houses, 1920-1998, contains pamphlets put out by the presses and publishing houses affiliated with the Communist Party of the United States; these include: International Publishers, New Century Publishers, and the Workers Library Publishers. The pamphlets from the three publishing houses are separated by either author or subject. Prominent authors represented in the collection are Earl Browder, William Z. Foster, Elizabeth Gurley Flynn, Herbert Aptheker, and Gus Hall. Also included in this series are catalogs, publicity materials, fliers and brochures from CPUSA newspapers, the Daily World, the People's Weekly World, and the People's World.
Series V: Oversize, 1932-1949, contains materials that are large and required separate housing. This consists of brochures, clippings, constitutions, fliers, and pamphlets. A majority of the materials are from New York State and New York City, but also originate with the Daily Worker, the Waterfront Section, and the Youth Communist League.
Historical Note
The Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA) was founded in 1919 by members of the left wing of the Socialist Party USA. The CPUSA played an important role in the labor movement, particularly in the building of the Congress of Industrial Organizations in the 1930s-1940s, in struggles for civil rights for African Americans. Its cultural initiatives in the 1930s attracted a number of prominent artists and intellectuals, and its struggles to attain and maintain its legality were an important chapter in the history of U.S. civil liberties.
In 2009, the Communist Party of the United States of America and the Library of the Reference Center for Marxist Studies donated its collection to the Tamiment Library.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library. There is no accession record associated with this collection.
In 2025, materials from accession 2019.056, which is associated with Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on Subjects (PE 029), were transferred to this collection.
Clippings (information artifacts); Catalogs.; Communists -- New York (State) -- New York -- Political activity.; Brochures.; Civil rights.; China -- Politics and government.; Women communists -- United States.; Civil rights -- United States.; African Americans -- Civil rights; Fliers (printed matter); Communism -- New York (State).; Bulletins.; Publications (documents); Pamphlets.; Communists -- New York (State); Communism -- New York (State) -- New York; Communism.; Communism -- United States.; Communism -- United States -- History.; Communism -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Communism -- United States -- 20th century; Antisemitism -- Soviet Union -- History -- 20th century.; Labor unions and communism.; Soviet Union.; Circular letters.; Soviet Union -- History.; Constitutions.; Antisemitism -- United States; Communists -- New York (State) -- New York.; Cuba.; Daily world (New York, N.Y.); Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley; Communist Party of the United States of America (Penn.); Young Communist League of the U.S.; Young Workers League of America; Young Workers Liberation League; Communist Party of the United States of America (Mass.); Communist Party of the United States of America (New York); Communist Party of the United States of America (Ohio); Communist Party U.S.A. (Opposition); Browder, Earl, 1891-1973; Aptheker, Herbert, 1915-2003.; Dennis, Eugene, 1905-1961; Daily Worker (New York); Communist Party of the United States of America. Negro Commission; Communist Party of the United States of America. Southern California District; Communist Party of the United States of America. Waterfront Section; Marx, Karl, 1818-1883; Lenin, Vladimir Il'ich, 1870-1924; Molotov, Vyacheslav Mikhaylovich, 1890-1986; Stalin, Joseph, 1878-1953; Foster, William Z., 1881-1961; Engels, Friedrich, 1820-1895; Bittelman, Alex, 1890-1982; Magil, A. B. (Abraham Bernard), 1905-2003; Minor, Robert, 1884-1952; Communist Party of the United States of America -- History; Davis, Benjamin J. (Benjamin Jefferson), 1903-1964; International Publishers; Communist Party of the United States of America (Ind.); Communist Party of the United States of America (Ill.); Communist Party of the United States of America (Calif.); Communist Party of the United States of America
- Series I: CPUSA General Files, 1920-2004; 4.25 Linear Feet 3 record cartons, 2 manuscript boxes, and 1 oversize shared box
  - 1926-1929 (Box 1)
  - 1930-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1960-1990 (Box 1)
  - undated (Box 1)
  - Agit Prop Commission (District 6), undated (Box 1)
  - Black Liberation Commission, 1971-1973 (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Central Committee, 1929-1934 (Box 1)
  - Central Committee, 1935-1988, undated (Box 1, Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Central Committee: Agit-Prop Commission/ Department, 1934-1935, undated (Box 1)
  - Central Committee: Jewish Buro, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Central Committee: Organization Commission, 1935, 1947 (Box 1, Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Central Committee: Reports to, 1977-1985, undated (Box 1)
  - Central Control Commission, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Circular Letters and Memoranda, 1930-1952, undated (Box 1)
  - Circular Letters and Memoranda, 1960-1991, undated (Box 1)
  - Coal Commission, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Commission on African-American Equality, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Communism (General and Anti-): Articles, 1934-1962, undated (Box 1)
  - Communist Party Campaign Committee, undated (Box 1)
  - Communist Party Defense Committee (Elizabeth Gurley Flynn, Chairman), 1949 (Box 1)
  - Communist Party Labor Coalition, undated (Box 1)
  - Constitutions, 1938-1959 (Box 1)
  - Constitutions, 1967-1987 (Box 1, Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Courses and Curriculum, 1937, undated (Box 1)
  - Courses and Curriculum: Party Organization, 1934, undated (Box 1)
  - Cultural Division: Artists Section, 1947, undated (Box 1)
  - Department of Justice on "Communist Front Organizations", 1953 (Box 1)
  - Election Campaign Handbook, 1940 (Box 2)
  - Election Platforms, 1936-1952, 1968, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Elections (General), 1968-2004 (Box 2)
  - Elections: Hall/Davis Campaign, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Elections: Hall/Tyner Campaign, 1972-1976 (Box 2)
  - Erista Manifesto, undated (Box 2)
  - Fliers and Brochures I, 1930-1989, undated (Box 2)
  - Fliers and Brochures II, 1930-1989, undated (Box 2)
  - Greek-American Club, 1948 (Box 2)
  - Gus Hall - Benjamin Davis Defense Committee, 1964, undated (Box 2)
  - Harlem Committee to Free Henry Winston, undated (Box 2)
  - Health Commission, 1990, undated (Box 2)
  - Historians' Group, 1958 (Box 2)
  - History, circa 1955 (Box 2)
  - History / Anniversaries, 1937-2005 (Box 2, Box 15, Folder 4, Box Shared Tamiment 186, Folder 12)
  - Ideological Conference, 1989 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Labor Committee, 1949, undated (Box 2)
  - National Auto Commission, undated (Box 2)
  - National Board, 1945, undated (Box 2)
  - National Campaign Committee (Foster/Ford), 1932 (Box 2)
  - National Campaign Committee (Browder/Ford), 1936-1940 (Box 2)
  - National Committee, 1939-1959 (Box 2)
  - National Committee, 1960-1972, 1990, 1996, undated (Box 2, Box 15, Folder 6)
  - National Committee: Public Affairs Department, 1950 (Box 2)
  - National Conventions, 1930-1987 (Box 2, Box 15, Folder 7-8)
  - National Conventions, 1957-1959 (Box 2)
  - National Conventions, 1960 (Box 2)
  - National Conventions, 1969-1972 (Box 2)
  - National Conventions, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
  - National Conventions, 1979 (Box 2)
  - National Conventions, 1983-1991 (Box 2)
  - National Conventions: Souvenir Book, undated (Box 2)
  - National Economics Commission, 1969 (Box 2)
  - National Education Department: Discussion Guides, 1938-1949 (Box 2)
  - National Education Department: Discussion Guides, 1950-1951 (Box 2)
  - National Education Department: Discussion Guides I, 1953-1984 (Box 3)
  - National Education Department: Discussion Guides II, 1953-1984 (Box 3)
  - National Education Department: Discussion Guides, undated (Box 3)
  - National Education Department: Discussion Guides: Political Education Campaign, 1944-1945 (Box 3)
  - National Education Department: Memoranda, 1949-1962 (Box 3)
  - National Education Department: Publications, 1944-1960, undated (Box 3)
  - National Election Campaign Committee, 1952 (Box 3)
  - National Environmental Commission, 1994- (Box 3)
  - National Farm Commission, 1955, undated (Box 3)
  - National Health Commission, 1996 (Box 3)
  - National Labor Department, undated (Box 3)
  - National Negro Commission, 1938, undated (Box 3)
  - National Organization Commission/Department, 1950, 1955 (Box 3)
  - National Organizing Committee to Found a Communist Youth Organization, 1982 (Box 3)
  - National Party Building Tour (Speeches and Reports by Gus Hall), 1981-1985 (Box 3, Box 15, Folder 9)
  - National Teachers Commission, undated (Box 3)
  - National Veterans Commission, 1947 (Box 3)
  - National Women's Commission, 1949-1954 (Box 3)
  - National Youth Commission, 1965, undated (Box 3, Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Nelson, Steve (Committee(s) to Defend Pittsburgh Five), 1951-1954 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1933-1960 (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets, 1930-1975 (Box 3, Box 16, Folder 1-2)
  - Pamphlets, 1950-1959 (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets, 1960-1989 (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets, 1990- (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets I, undated (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets II, undated (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets: "Of the People for the People: Pictorial Highlights of Fifty Years of the Communist Party of the United States of America", 1969 (Box 3)
  - Political Committee, 1927-1939 (Box 3)
  - Press Releases, 1948 (Box 3)
  - Press Releases, 1951-1961 (Box 3)
  - Program of the Communist Party of the United States of America, 1966-1969, undated (Box 3, Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Publicity Department, undated (Box 3)
  - Southern Regional Council, 1953, undated (Box 3)
  - Speakers Bureau, undated (Box 3)
  - Statements to the Press/Public, Open Letters, 1931-1970, undated (Box 3)
  - Steel and Metal Workers Commission, 1971-1976 (Box 3)
  - Trial of the Twelve, 1941-1949, undated (Box 3)
  - Waterfront Section, 1939-1949, undated (Box 3)
  - Winston Enrollment Campaign Committee, undated (Box 3)
  - "World Communism Today" Poster, circa 1960 (Box 3)
- Series II: CPUSA State and Local Files, 1929-1987; 3.5 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons and 1 manuscript box
  Arrangement
  This series has been arranged into two subseries. Files in Subseries II.A are arranged with New York State files listed first, followed by files arranged alphabetically. Files in Subseries II.B are arranged alphabetically. The subseries arrangement of the records is as follows:
  Subseries II.A New York, 1929-1984
  Subseries II.B Other, 1930-1987
  - Sub-series A: New York, 1929-1984; 2.5 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons and 1 manuscript box
    - New York State, 1929-1935 (Box 4)
    - New York State, 1936-1939 (Box 4)
    - New York State, 1940-1975 (Box 4, Box 16, Folder 4)
    - New York State, 1947-1949 (Box 4)
    - New York State, 1950-1959 (Box 4)
    - New York State, 1960-1979 (Box 4)
    - New York State, 1980- (Box 4)
    - New York State, undated (Box 4)
    - New York State: Education Department, 1936 (Box 4)
    - New York State: Education Department, 1937-1939 (Box 4)
    - New York State: Education Department, 1940-1947 (Box 4)
    - New York State: Education Department, 1948-1949 (Box 4)
    - New York State: Education Department, 1950 (Box 4)
    - New York State: Education Department, 1951-1968 (Box 4)
    - New York State: Education Department, undated (Box 4)
    - New York State: Election Campaign Committee, 1929-1958, undated (Box 4)
    - New York State: Housing Commission, 1939, undated (Box 4)
    - New York State: Legislative Bureau, 1947 (Box 4)
    - New York State: Pamphlets and Publications, 1938-1987 (Box 4)
    - New York State: Pamphlets and Publications, undated (Box 4)
    - New York State: Veterans Commission, undated (Box 4)
    - New York State: Women's Commission, 1949 (Box 4)
    - New York State: Youth Division, 1942-1946 (Box 4)
    - New York (District #2), 1931-1935 (Box 4)
    - New York (District #2), 1936, 1967, 1984, undated (Box 5)
    - New York (District #2): Disciplinary Actions, 1935 (Box 5)
    - New York (District #2): Fliers, 1929-1936, undated (Box 5)
    - New York (District #2): Pamphlets and Publications, 1931-1935, undated (Box 5)
    - Bedford-Stuyvesant, 1949 (Box 5)
    - Bronx County, 1939-1949, undated (Box 5)
    - Brooklyn, 1939-1972, undated (Box 5)
    - Erie County (Buffalo, NY), 1958 (Box 5)
    - Inwood Club of the Communist Party, undated (Box 5)
    - New York County, 1938-1948, undated (Box 5)
    - Queens County, 1938-1952, undated (Box 5)
    - Westchester County, 1936-1949 (Box 5)
    - Harlem Communist Election Campaign Committee for the Re-Election of Benjamin J. Davis, undated (Box 5)
    - Harlem Section / Division I, 1934-1970, undated (Box 5)
    - Harlem Section / Division II, 1935-1970, undated (Box 5)
    - Lower East Side Communist Party, undated (Box 5)
    - New York City, 1929-1935 (Box 5)
    - New York City, 1940-1981 (Box 5)
    - New York City, undated (Box 5)
  - Sub-series B: Other, 1930-1987; 2.5 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons and 1 manuscript box
    - California, 1934-1956, undated (Box 5)
    - California: Southern California District, 1966-1968, undated (Box 5)
    - Colorado, 1939 (Box 5)
    - Connecticut, 1932-1987 (Box 5)
    - Connecticut: Fishman, Joelle Campaign, 1974-1976, undated (Box 5)
    - D.C./ Virginia, 1982 (Box 5, Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Illinois, 1930-1939 (Box 5)
    - Illinois I, 1940-1949 (Box 5)
    - Illinois II, 1940-1949 (Box 5)
    - Illinois, 1950- (Box 5)
    - Illinois, undated (Box 5)
    - Illinois: Chicago, 1931-1935, undated (Box 5)
    - Illinois: Legislative Bureau: Election Campaign Handbook, 1939 (Box 5)
    - Indiana, undated (Box 5)
    - Maryland: Baltimore, 1950, undated (Box 5)
    - Maryland and District of Columbia, undated (Box 5)
    - Massachusetts, 1930-1937 (Box 5)
    - Massachusetts, 1938-1939 (Box 5)
    - Massachusetts, 1940-1946 (Box 5)
    - Massachusetts, undated (Box 5)
    - Michigan, 1947-1948, 1996, undated (Box 6, Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Minnesota, 1970 (Box 6)
    - Missouri, 1936-1941 (Box 6)
    - Montana, 1942 (Box 6)
    - New Jersey, 1938-1949, undated (Box 6)
    - New England District, 1933-1937, undated (Box 6)
    - North Carolina, 1940-1953 (Box 6)
    - Ohio, 1932-1938 (Box 6, Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Pennsylvania (Eastern), 1955-1973, undated (Box 6)
    - Pennsylvania (Western), 1936-1952, undated (Box 6)
    - Wisconsin, 1941-1972 (Box 6)
- Series III: Affiliated and Youth Organizations, 1918-1987; 2.5 Linear Feet in 1 record carton and 3 manuscript boxes
  - Communist Labor Party of America, 1918 (Box 6)
  - Communist Party of the United States of America (Opposition), 1933-1934 (Box 6)
  - Communist Party of the United States of America (Opposition), 1935-1936, undated (Box 6)
  - Communist Party of the United States of America (Opposition): Workers Age Publishing Association (New York, NY), 1932-1935 (Box 6)
  - Communist Political Association, 1944-1945 (Box 6)
  - Labor Youth League, 1949-1952 (Box 6)
  - Labor Youth League, 1953-1955, undated (Box 6)
  - Labor Youth League: National Conventions, 1950, 1954 (Box 6)
  - Labor Youth League: New York Organizing Committee for a Labor Youth League, 1949, undated (Box 6)
  - PR Club, Communist Party (Expelled) (New York, NY), 1950 (Box 6)
  - WEB DuBois Clubs of America, 1962-1967 (Box 6, Box 16, Folder 8)
  - WEB DuBois Clubs of America, 1968-1969, undated (Box 6)
  - WEB DuBois Clubs of America, undated (Box 6)
  - Young Communist League I, 1927-1935, 1942, 1984, undated (Box 6, Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Young Communist League II, 1927-1935, 1984-, undated (Box 6)
  - Young Communist League: Conventions, 1936-1939, 1986- (Box 6)
  - Young Communist League: Illinois, 1938, undated (Box 6)
  - Young Communist League: Massachusetts (Cambridge, Boston, Harvard), 1933-1940 (Box 6)
  - Young Communist League: National Education Department, 1933-1943 (Box 7)
  - Young Communist League: New York: Brooklyn College, 1938, undated (Box 7)
  - Young Communist League: New York: Bronx County, undated (Box 7)
  - Young Communist League: New York: City College Branch, 1936-1938 (Box 7)
  - Young Communist League: New York: Jefferson High School Branch, undated (Box 7)
  - Young Communist League: New York District, 1939, undated (Box 7, Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Young Communist League: New York State, 1936-1943, undated (Box 7)
  - Young Communist League: Pamphlets and Publications, 1933-1943 (Box 7)
  - Young Communist League: Pamphlets and Publications, 1982-1987 (Box 7)
  - Young Communist League: Pamphlets and Publications, undated (Box 7)
  - Young Workers (Communist) League of America, 1925-1928 (Box 7)
  - Young Workers League of America, undated (Box 7)
  - Young Workers Liberation League, 1970 (Box 7)
  - Young Workers Liberation League, 1971-1977 (Box 13, Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Young Workers Liberation League, 1976-1981 (Box 13)
  - Young Workers Liberation League, undated (Box 13)
- Series IV: Presses and Publishing Houses, 1920-1998; 5.5 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons and 3 manuscript boxes
  - Daily People's World, 1948, undated (Box 13, Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Daily Worker, 1925-1968, undated (Box 14, Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Daily Worker: Catalogue, "Books for Workers", undated (Box 14)
  - Daily Worker: Pamphlets, 1943-1946, undated (Box 14)
  - Daily World, 1968-1972, undated (Box 14, Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Hour Publishers, undated (Box 14)
  - International Publishers: Catalogs and Fliers I, 1926-1998 (Box 14)
  - International Publishers: Catalogs and Fliers II, 1926-1998 (Box 14)
  - International Publishers: Pamphlets I, 1928-1939 (Box 14)
  - International Publishers: Pamphlets II, 1928-1939 (Box 14)
  - International Publishers: Pamphlets I, 1940-1949 (Box 14)
  - International Publishers: Pamphlets II, 1940-1949 (Box 8)
  - International Publishers: Pamphlets, 1950-1959, undated (Box 8)
  - International Publishers: Pamphlets: African-Americans/Civil Rights, 1932-1942, undated (Box 8)
  - International Publishers: Pamphlets: Communist Manifesto and History of, 1932-1938 (Box 8)
  - International Publishers: Pamphlets: Engels, Frederick, 1933-1950 (Box 8)
  - International Publishers: Pamphlets: Japan, 1941-1942 (Box 8)
  - International Publishers: Pamphlets: Lenin, V.I. I, 1932-1940 (Box 8)
  - International Publishers: Pamphlets: Lenin, V.I. II, 1932-1940 (Box 8)
  - International Publishers: Pamphlets: Mao, Tse-Tung, undated (Box 8)
  - International Publishers: Pamphlets: Marx, Karl, 1933, 1983 (Box 8)
  - International Publishers: Pamphlets: May Day, 1935-1947 (Box 8)